Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴：邓雄飞、张大伟
压制&&特效：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
校对：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
特别感谢：裘宗燕教授
计算机程序的构造和解释
元循环求值器 II
Metacircular Evaluator II
教授：目前为止
PROFESSOR: Well, let's see.
我们学的东西都非常有趣
What we did so far was a lot of fun,
但它有什么实际的用途吗？
was it useful for anything?
我想答案是“是的”
I suppose the answer is going to be yes.
这些元循环求值器
If these metacircular interpreters
非常值得琢磨
are a valuable thing to play with.
我花了大概
I spend, say
我曾花了半年时间
there have been times I spend 50% of my time, over a year,
用上节课你们见到的
trying various design alternatives
那种元循环求值器来试验
by experimenting with them with metacircular interpreters--
各种各样不同的设计
metacircular interpreters like the sort you just saw.
用元循环求值是因为
Metacircular is because
#TBD
they are defined in terms of themselves in such a way
that the language they interpret contains itself.
这样的求值器是一种的媒介
Such interpreters are a convenient medium
帮助我们探索语言问题
for exploring language issues.
如果你想添加一个新的FEATURE
If you want to try adding a new feature,
这就是小菜一碟
it's sort of a snap, it's easy,
你只需要稍作修改 然后观察结果
you just do it and see what happens.
在尝试了一会儿新语言后
You play with that language for a while you say,
你可能觉得它不好 就把它扔到一边去了
gee, I'm didn't like that, you throw it away.
或者你也想研究
Or you might want to see what
不同的绑定策略的差异
the difference is if you'd make a slight difference in the binding strategy,
或者是一些更复杂的东西
or some more complicated things that might occur.
事实上 这些元循环求值器
In fact, these metacircular interpreters
非常适合作为交换媒介
are an excellent medium for people
承载人们关于语言设计想法
exchanging ideas about language design,
因为它们易于理解
because they're pretty easy to understand,
它们短小、紧凑而且简洁
and they're short, and compact, and simple.
如果我有一些点子
If I have some idea
想让其它人评论一下
that I want somebody to criticize
比如Indiana大学的Dan Friedman教授
like say, Dan Friedman at Indiana,
我就编写一个小型的元循环求值器
I'd write a little metacircular interpreter
然后把求值器作为附件给他发一封电子邮件
send him some network mail with this interpreter in it.
他就可以在电脑上按照并运行这个求值器
He could whip it up on his machine and play with it
可能他会觉得这个设计并不好
and say, that's no good.
然后他会给我回一封邮件
And then send it back to me and say,
“为什么不试试这个 这个更好一点”
well, why don't you try this one, it's a little better.
所以我将会讲一些这方面的技术
So I want to show you some of that technology.
因为在设计你自己的特定用途语言时
See, because, really, it's the essential, simple technology
这种简单的技术非常重要
for getting started in designing your own languages for particular purposes.
我们试着先在Lisp中
Let's start by adding
添加一个非常简单的FEATURE
a very simple feature to a Lisp.
在这之前 我先来谈谈FEATURE吧
Now, one thing I want to tell you about is features, before I start.
很多语言添加了大量的FEATURE
There are many languages that have made a mess of themselves
把它们本身搞得混乱不堪
by adding huge numbers of features.
计算机科学家有一个笑话
Computer scientists have a joke
“这不是BUG 这是FEATURE”
about bugs that transform it to features all the time.
而我宁愿认为
But I like to think of it is that
很多系统都在遭受着“功能蔓延”的影响
many systems suffer from what's called creeping featurism.
比方说
Which is that
George希望系统中有某个FEATURE
George has a pet feature he'd like in the system,
他就把它加入了系统
so he adds it.
Harry也想着
And then Harry says, go says
这个系统现在也不是我喜欢的那个了
gee, this system is no longer what exactly I like,
然后加入了自己最喜欢的FEATURE
so I'm going to add my favorite feature.
Jim也这样做
And then Jim adds his favorite feature.
一段时间过后
And, after a while,
操作手册就多达500页
the thing has a manual 500 pages long
以至于没人能看得懂
that no one can understand.
有时候也可能只是
And sometimes it's the same person
同一个人在添加FEATURE
who writes all of these features
也会导致同样糟糕的结果
and produces this terribly complicated thing.
很多情况下 比如编辑器
In some cases, like editors,
具有很多FEATURE就很合理
it's sort of reasonable to have lots of features,
因为你想要能够完成
because there are a lot of things you want to be able to do
各种不同的事情
and many of them arbitrary.
但对计算机语言来说
But in computer languages,
我认为太多的FEATURE
I think it's a disaster
是一个灾难
to have too much stuff in them.
#TBD
The other alternative you get into is something called feeping creaturism,
假设你有一个盒子
which is where you have a box
它有一个鼠标和花哨的显示器
which has a display, a fancy display, and a mouse,
#TBD
and there is all sorts of complexity associated with all this fancy IO.
And your computer language becomes
#TBD
a dismal, little, tiny thing that barely works
because of all the swapping, and disk twitching, and so on,
#TBD
caused by your Windows system.
每当你使用计算机的时候
And every time you go near the computer,
鼠标处理进程就会唤醒
the mouse process wakes up and says,
你有什么事情要我做的吗？
gee do you have something for me to do,
然后又回去休眠
and then it goes back to sleep.
如果你的胳膊肘不小心碰到了鼠标
And if you accidentally push mouse with you elbow,
一大堆烟雾就会从你的电脑出来 类似于这样
a big puff of smoke comes out of your computer and things like that.
这就是由于添加FEATURE
So two ways to disastrously
导致系统不能用的两种典型情况
destroy a system by adding features.
现在我们要添加的是 一个非常简单的FEATURE
But try right now to add a little, simple feature.
这个FEATURE非常好
This actually is a good one,
事实上 Lisp中就有这个FEATURE
and in fact, real Lisps have it.
我们都知道
As you've seen,
像+、*这样的过程
there are procedures like plus and times
可以接受不定数目的参数
that take any number of arguments.
因此我们就可以写
So we can write things
(+ (* A X X)
like the sum of the product of a and x and x,
(* B X) C)
and the product of b and x and c.
这里可以看到
As you can see here,
+有两到三个参数
addition takes three arguments or two arguments,
*也有两到三个参数
multiplication takes two arguments or three arguments,
不管多少个参数都同样可以计算
taking numbers of arguments all of which are to be treated in the same way.
支持不定数目的参数 这一点非常有用
This is a valuable thing, indefinite numbers of arguments.
而我上节课所讲的Lisp求值器
Yet the particular Lisp system that I show you
只能处理固定数目的参数
is one where the numbers of arguments is fixed,
因为我要用BIND过程中的PAIR-UP过程
because I had to match the arguments against the formal parameters
让形式参数与实际参数一一对应
in the binder, where there's a pairup.
假如我想能够定义像这样的过程
Well, I'd like to be able to define new procedures like this
它们可以接收任意个数的参数
that can have any number of arguments.
这个问题有好几部分
Well there's several parts to this problem.
首先是合适的语法描述
The first part is coming up with the syntactic specification,
我们需要能够标注额外的参数
some way of notating the additional arguments,
标注那些不知道个数的参数
of which you don't know how many there are.
另外就是
And then there's the other thing,
一旦我们标注出来后
which is once we've notated it,
我们怎样解释这些个记号
how are we going to interpret that notation
才能得到
so as to do the right thing,
正确的结果呢？
whatever the right thing is?
让我们来考虑一种
So let's consider an example of a sort of thing
我们可能会遇到的情况
we might want to be able to do.
比如说
So an example might be,
我想要定义这样的一个过程
that I might want to be able to define a procedure
它有一个必选参数X
which is a procedure of one required argument x
还有个可选参数 -- 或者说一堆参数
and a non-required -- bunch of arguments,
我不知道它们的数目 就记作Y吧
I don't know how many there are, called y.
X是必选的
So x is required,
然而有很多参数Y
and there are many y's,
这些参数形成的表 -- 我就记作Y
many arguments-- y will be the list of them.
写好了参数列表
Now, with such a thing,
我现在要这样定义过程体
we might be able to say something like,
我要对每一个元素都做同样的处理
map-- I'm going to do something to every one--
(MAP (LAMBDA (U)
of that procedure of one argument u,
(* X U)) Y)
which multiplies x by u, and we'll apply that to y.
这里 我用了一个“点号”
I've used a dot here
来表明点号后面的东西
to indicate that the thing after this
是剩下的所有参数构成的表
is a list of all the rest of the arguments.
这就是一个语法规范
I'm making a syntactic specification.
为什么这样来写呢？
Now, what this depends upon,
这种语法规范之所以合理
the reason why this is sort of a reasonable thing to do,
是因为Lisp的源码读取器
is because this happens to be a syntax
刚好使用这种语法
that's used in the Lisp reader
来表示序对
for representing conses.
我们之前没有介绍过
We've never introduced that before.You never see.
你在自己尝试的时候可能遇到过
You may have seen when playing with the system
当你调用(CONS X Y)时
if you cons two things together, you get the
你会得到 X . Y
first, space, dot, the second, space--
准确来说是(X . Y)
the first, space, dot, space, the second
两边还有括号
with parentheses around the whole thing.
举例来说吧
So that, for example,
这里的(X . Y)对应着一个序对
this x dot y corresponds to a pair,
X是CAR部分 Y是CDR部分
which has got an x in it and a y in it.
你们目前为止见过的其它记号
The other notations that you've seen so far
是像
are things like, like
(LAMBDA (X Y Z) ...)这样的
a procedure of arguments x and y and z which do things
它们则是像这样的
and that looks like--
就拿形式参数表来说
Just looking at the bound variable list,
它实际上是这样
it looks like this,
这里分别是 X、Y、Z和空表
x, y, z, and the empty thing.
如果我有一个想要与之匹配的参数表的话
If I have a list of arguments I wish to match this against,
假设实际参数表是'(1 2 3)
I have a list of arguments one, two, three,
我想把它们和形参相匹配
I want to match these against.
所以这里 可能有个三个元素的表
OK? So I might have here a list of three things,
分别是1、2、3
one, two, three.
用'(1 2 3)来匹配'(X Y Z)
And I want to match x, y, z against one, two, three.
很显然1和X相匹配
Well, it's clear that the one matches the x,
因为我可以顺着这个结构来
because I can just sort of follow the structure,
2和Y相匹配
and the two matches the y,
3和Z相匹配
and the three matches the z.
假设我现在要把这个(X . Y)
But now, supposing I were to compare this x dot y.
这个是(X . Y)
this is x dot y--
如果我想把它跟'(1 2 3)相匹配的话
supposing I compare that with a list of three arguments, one, two, three.
我们再来看
Let's look at that again.
这里是1、2、3
One, two, three--
我可以沿着这里遍历
Well, I can walk along here
会发现 1和X相匹配
and say, oh yes, x matches the one,
而Y和'(2 3)相匹配
Ah, the y matches the list, which is two and three.
所以这里选用的表示法
So the notation I'm choosing here
对于Lisp来说是非常自然的
is one that's very natural for Lisp system.
所以我就选择用这个记号
But I'm going to choose this as a notation
来表示数目不定的参数
for representing a bunch of arguments.
还有一种可能性
Now, there's an alternative possibility.
#TBD
If I don't want to take one special out,
or two special ones out or something like that,
如果我不想那样的话
if I don't want to do that,
如果我想像+那样
if I want to talk about
一下子引用所有的参数
just the list of all the arguments like in addition，
那么我就应该把参数列表写成
well then the argument list I'm going to choose to be
(LAMBDA X ...)
that procedure of all the arguments x, which does something with x
举例来说
And which, for example,
如果我定义一个过程
if I take the procedure,
它把接收所有的参数
which takes all the arguments x
然后返回一个由它们组成的表X
and returned the list of them,
返回的结果就是过程的参数表 明白吗？
OK? That's list. That's the procedure list.
这又是怎么回事呢？
How does this work?
确实 本例中我有的是形式参数表#TBD
Well, indeed what I had as the bound variable list in this case,
不管它们是什么 都要与实际参数相匹配
whatever it is, is being matched against a list of arguments.
现在 这个符号就是所有的实际参数了
This symbol now is all of the arguments.
所以 我选择使用这个特定的语法规范
And so this is the choice I'm making for a particular syntactic specification,
来描述那些
for the description of procedures
接收不定数目参数的过程
which take indefinite numbers of arguments.
一共就两种情况，上面这种和下面这种
There are two cases of it, this one and this one.
当你构建新的语法描述的时候，一定要注意，不要与现有的语法混淆或者矛盾
When you make syntactic specifications, it's important that it's unambiguous, that neither of these can be confused with a representation we already have, this one.
引入了新的语法描述，我也总是可以分清是接收固定数目的参数，还是一定固定参数后再接不定数目的参数，更或者是参数的个数完全不确定全部由x来表示
I can always tell whether I have a fixed number of explicitly named arguments made by these formal parameters, or a fixed number of named formal parameters followed by a thing which picks up all the rest of them, or a list of all the arguments which will be matched against this particular formal parameter called x, because these are syntactically distinguishable.
有很多语言都是由于语法描述方面出现了混淆或者矛盾导致语言解释器的错误
Many languages make terrible errors in that form where whole segments of interpretation are cut off, because there are syntactic ambiguities in the language.
比如 类ALGOL语言的嵌套if问题
They are the traditional problems with ALGOL like languages having to do with the nesting of ifs in the predicate part.
现在我已经告诉你们可行的语法了，接下来要怎么做呢？
In any case, now, so I've told you about the syntax, now, what are we going to do about the semantics of this?
我们如何来解释它？
How do we interpret it?
其实很简单
Well this is just super easy.
现在我来修改一下元循环
I'm going to modify the metacircular interpreter to do it.
只需要修改一行
And that's a one liner.
在这里
There it is.
把pair-up修改一下就行
I'm changing the way you pair things up.
pair-up就是那个用来匹配形参与实参的过程
Here's the procedure that pairs the variables, the formal parameters, with the arguments that were passed from the last description of the metacircular interpreter.
大部分地方都不需要修改
And here's some things that are the same as they were before.
如果变量列表为空，而且值的列表也是空，就返回空列表
In other words, if the list of variables is empty, then if the list of values is empty, then I have an empty list.
否则，就是值太多了，也即变量列表为空而值列表不是空的
Otherwise, I have too many arguments, that is, if I have empty variables but not empty values.
如果值列表为空，但是变量列表不为空，那么就是实参给少了
If I have empty values, but the variables are not empty, I have too few arguments.
如果变量是一个符号，开始有意思了，这是一种特殊情况，这是一个符号尾
The variables are a symbol-- interesting case-- then, what I should do is say, oh yes, this is the special case that I have a symbolic tail.
情况就像这里的一样
I have here a thing just like we looked over here.
tail部分的y是一个符号
This is a tail which is a symbol, y.
它不是nil
It's not a nil.
也不是空列表，这里的符号尾x就是最开始的那种情况
It's not the empty list. Here's a symbolic tail that is just the very beginning of the tail.
不是另外的情况
There is nothing else.
这种情况下，我就用这个符号去匹配整个值列表
In that case, I wish to match that variable with all the values and add that to the pairing that I'm making.
否则，我就回到以往的正常情况来一一匹配
Otherwise, I go through the normal arrangement of making up the whole pairing.
我认为这很容易理解
I suppose that's very simple.
就是这些
And that's all there is to it.
现在  答疑时间
And now I'll answer some questions.
有什么问题吗？
The first one-- Are there any questions?
你说
Yes?
你能再解释一下第三种形式吗？
AUDIENCE: Could you explain that third form?
这个？
PROFESSOR: Third form. This one? OK.
或许你用表结构来思考它会更容易理解一些
Well, maybe we should look at the thing as a piece of list structure.
这是一个过程，包含一个lambda
This is a procedure which contains a lambda.
我来画出表示上面这个过程的表结构
I'm just looking at the list structure which represents this.
这里是x
Here's x.
这些是我们的符号
These are our symbols.
过程体就是x而已
And then the body is nothing but x.
如果我来查找这个过程的形参部分，取整个结构的CADR，返回一个符号x
If I were looking for the bound variable list part of this procedure, I would go looking at the CADR, and I'd find a symbol.
所以，很自然地，在pair-up中，我就用一个符号去匹配整个实参的列表
So the, naturally, which is this pairup thing I just showed you, is going to be matching a symbolic object against a list of arguments that were passed.
这个符号与实参的列表相绑定
And it will bind that symbol to the list of arguments.
上面这种情况，如果我用CADR，得到这样的结构去匹配实参列表
In this case, if I'm looking for it, the match will be against this in the bound variable list position.
这里的x就匹配到整个实参的列表然后返回x这个列表，这就是这个过程所做的事
Now, if what this does is it gets a list of arguments and returns it, that's list. That's what the procedure is.
好的
Oh well, thank you.
大家休息一下吧
Let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
元循环求值器 II
我们接着来看
PROFESSOR: Well let's see.
我将要介绍另一种Lisp变式，这项feature非常出名，早期的很多Lisp实现都有它
Now, I'm going to tell you about a rather more substantial variation, one that's a famous variation that many early Lisps had.
它被称为变量的动态绑定
It's called dynamic binding of variables.
我们现在来研究一下
And we'll investigate a little bit about that right now.
我先来介绍一下是什么情况导致人们会有动态绑定这样的想法的
I'm going to first introduce this by showing you the sort of thing that would make someone want this idea.
我不具体说是到底是什么情况，我只来举一些例子，你们说不定也会有同样的想法的
I'm not going to tell what it is yet, I'm going to show you why you might want it.
假设，我们再来考虑sum这个过程，对一串东西求和
Suppose, for example, we looked at the sum procedure again for summing up a bunch of things.
(define sum (lambda (term a next b) (cond ((> a b) 0) (else (+ (term a) (sum term (next a) next b))))))
To be that procedure, of a term, lower bound, method of computing the next index, and upper bound, such that, if a is greater than b then the result is 0, otherwise, it's the sum, of the term, procedure, applied to a and the result of adding up, terms, with the next a being the a, the next procedure passed along, and the upper bound being passed along.
当我使用sum过程的时候，我可以这样来用
Blink, blink, blink-- Now, when I use this sum procedure, I can use it, for example, like this.
(define sum-powers (lambda (a b n) (sum (lambda (x) (expt x n)) a 1+ b)))
We can define the sum of the powers to be, for example, sum of a bunch of powers x to the n, to be that procedure of a, b, and n-- lower bound, the upper bound, and n-- which is sum, of lambda of x, the procedure of one argument x, which exponentiates x to the n, with the a, the incrementer, and b, being passed along.
计算x^n
So we're adding up x to n, given an x.
x从a到b取值，加1递增
x takes on values from a to b, incrementing by one.
我也可以写 -- 对了
I can also write the-- That's right.
乘积
Product, excuse me.
product-powers
The product of a bunch of powers.
名字有点奇怪
It's a strange name.
还是不改了
I'm going to leave it there.
有点怪，就按原来的吧
Weird-- I write up what I have. I'm sure that's right.
如果我想写product-powers，That was 12 brain cells, that double-take.[此句不明了]
And if I want the product of a bunch of powers-- That was 12 brain cells, that double-take.
这个过程就像刚才的sum-powers差不多
I can for example use the procedure which is like sum, which is for making products, but it's similar to that, that you've seen before.
也是一个有三个参数的过程
There's a procedure of three arguments again.
过程具体为(product (lambda (x) (expt x n)) a 1+ b)
Which is the product of terms that are constructed, or factors in this case, constructed from exponentiating x to the n, where I start with a, I increment, and I go to b.
你可能马上就意识到一些问题
Now, there's some sort of thing here that should disturb you immediately.
它们看起来几乎一样
These look the same.
为什么要重复写代码呢？
Why am I writing this code so many times?
现在就和之前我们遇到的情况很相似了
Here I am, in the same boat I've been in before.
构造一个抽象不是挺好的吗？
Wouldn't it be nice to make an abstraction here?
如何构建良好的抽象呢？
What's an example of a good abstraction to make?
我看到有一些完全相同的代码
Well, I see some codes that's identical.
这有一段，还有这里
Here's one, and here's another.
所以我应该把它们提取出来
And so maybe I should be able to pull that out.
所以我就会想，sum-powers可以用名为nth-powers的过程来表示
I should be able to say, oh yes, the sum of the powers could be written in terms of something called the nth power procedure.
假如有人想写一个稍微不同的过程
Imagine somebody wanted to write a slightly different procedure that looks like this.
(define sum-powers (lambda (a b n)
The sum powers to be a procedure of a, b, and n, as the result of summing up the nth power.
(sum nth-power a 1+ b)
We're going to give a name to that idea, for starting at a, going by one, and ending at b.
相似地，我用这种方式来重写product-powers
And similarly, I might want to write the product powers this way, abstracting out this idea.
应该这样
I might want this.
(define product-powers (lambda (a b n) (product nth-powers a 1+ b)))
Product powers, to be a procedure of a, b, and n, which is the product of the nth power operation on a with the incrementation and b being my arguments for the analogous-thing product.
我们还需要定义过程nth-powers，我把它写在这边
And I'd like to be able to define, I'd like to be able to define nth power-- I'll put it over here.
写在上面
I'll put it at the top.
这个过程就应该是 (define nth-powers (lambda (x) (expt x n)))
--to be, in fact, my procedure of one argument x which is the result of exponentiating x to the n.
但是我遇到一个问题
But I have a problem.
我们用环境模型来解释这一段代码，但是找不到n的定义
My environment model, that is my means of interpretation for the language that we've defined so far, does not give me a meaning for this n.
因为，在这个过程内，n是自由变量
Because, as you know, this n is free in this procedure.
环境模型告诉我们自由变量的值取决于过程被定义时所在的环境
The environment model tells us that the meaning of a free variable is determined in the environment in which this procedure is defined.
假设所有的过程就像我在黑板上写的这样来定义，nth-powers就定义在全局环境下，没有n的定义
In a way I have written it, assuming these things are defined on the blackboard as is, this is defined in the global environment, where there is no end.
因此，n是未绑定的变量
Therefore, n is unbound variable.
这种写法很简洁，但是我们都希望n是这里的n和这里的n
But it's perfectly clear, to most of us, that we would like it to be this n and this n.
这样就太完美了
On the other hand, it would be nice.
当然我们也要确定这里的n是这里的n，这边的也一样
Certainly we've got to be careful here of keeping this to be this, and this one over here, wherever it is to be this one.
这种想法造就了一个非常著名的bug
Well, the desire to make this work has led to a very famous bug.
我来细说下这个bug
I'll tell you about the famous bug.
这张幻灯片
Look at this slide.
这是一种新的设计想法，动态绑定
This is an idea called dynamic binding.
不在过程定义时的环境下解释自由变量，而在调用过程的环境下解释被调用过程内部的自由变量
Where, instead of the free variable being interpreted in the environment of definition of a procedure, the free variable is interpreted as having its value in the environment of the caller of the procedure.
在这个系统中，你从调用程序的链中搜索自由变量，在这个例子里，nth-powers在product的内部被调用 -- sum也是相似的 -- product被product-powers调用，所以你看，product-powers绑定了变量n之后，nth-powers就可以解释自由变量n了
So what you have is a system where you search up the chain of callers of a particular procedure, and, of course, in this case, since nth power is called from inside product whatever it is-- I had to write our own sum which is the analogous procedure-- and product is presumably called from product powers, as you see over here, then since product powers bind with variable n , then nth powers n would be derived through that chain.
相似地，sum这边，nth-powers中的n会通过sum-powers sum这样的调用关系中解释自由变量n
Similarly, this n, the nth power in n in this case, would come through nth power here being called from inside sum.
它被sum调用了
You can see it being called from inside sum here.
对应这里的term
It's called term here.
sum在sum-powers内部被调用，而sum-powers绑定了变量n
But sum was called from inside of sum powers, which bound n.
因此nth-powers这里的n就得到了解释
Therefore, there would be an n available for that n to get it's value from.
这边白线以下的情况，就是我们所称的动态绑定
What we have below this white line plus over here, is what's called a dynamic binding view of the world.
用动态绑定的角度来解释，就可以正常运行
If that works, that's a dynamic binding view.
我们来看看，要怎么实现这个功能
Now, let's take a look, for example, at just what it takes to implement that.
非常简单
That's real easy.
事实上，最开始的Lisp实现凡是可以对自由变量进行解释的，都是用的动态绑定方法
In fact, the very first Lisps that had any interpretations of the free variables at all, had dynamic binding interpretations for the free variables.
APL就是用动态绑定来解释自由变量的，而不是静态绑定
APL has dynamic binding interpretation for the free variables, not lexical or static binding.
要实现动态绑定，要从eval下手
So, of course, the change is in eval.
只需修改两个地方就行
And it's really in two places.
第一个地方修改的更为简单
First of all, one thing we see, is that things become a little simpler.
如果是动态绑定的话，过程在定义的时候就无需关乎环境的问题
If I don't have to have the environment be the environment of definition for procedure, the procedure need not capture the environment at the time it's defined.
所以我们看到，在lambda表达式的这一行，只需要返回exp本身就行了，不需要像之前那样加上类型标签'closure并且和环境结构绑定在一起
And so if we look here at this slide, we see that the clause for a lambda expression, which is the way a procedure is defined, does not make up a thing which has a type closure and a attached environment structure.
就是exp本身
It's just the expression itself.
相应的，解读lambda过程的地方也要修改一些
And we'll decompose that some other way somewhere else.
另外要注意的是，在apply的时候必须要知道调用者的环境
The other thing we see is the applicator must be able to get the environment of the caller.
调用者的环境就在这里
The caller of a procedure is right here.
如果表达式是一个过程应用或者组合式，然后我们就执行过程，也就是操作符的值
If the expression we're evaluating is anpplication or a combination, then we're going to call a procedure which is the value of the operator.
调用者的环境就是我们当前的环境
The environment of the caller is the environment we have right here, available now.
所以我要把这个环境传递予apply
So all I have to do is pass that environment to the applicator, to apply.
我们再来看看apply，增加了一个环境参数，绑定参数的时候就来扩展这个环境，而不是去扩展原先绑定在'closure过程内的环境了
And if we look at that here, the only change we have to make is that fellow takes that environment and uses that environment for the purpose of extending that environment when abiding the formal parameters of the procedure to the arguments that were passed, not an environment that was captured in the procedure.
为什么早期的Lisp如此来实现呢？原因也很清楚，碰巧实现了
The reason why the first Lisps were implemented this way, is the sort of the obvious, accidental implementation.
然后大家也就习惯了
And, of course, as usual, people got used to it and liked it.
因此不少人就说Lisp就应该这样做
And there were some people said, this is the way to do it.
不幸地是这导致了不小的问题，最严重的一点是，动态绑定破坏了模块性
Unfortunately that causes some serious problems. The most important, serious problem in using dynamic binding is there's a modularity crisis that's involved it.
如果有两个人在一个大型系统上协同工作，其中一个重要的事情就是两个人的命名不能相互冲突
If two people are working together on some big system, then an important thing to want is that the names used by each one don't interfere with the names of the other.
这一点很重要，不能说 你使用了我代码中的命名就导致我的代码停止工作
It's important that when I invent some segment of code that no one can make my code stop working by using my names that I use internal to my code, internal to his code.
然而，很明显地 动态绑定和特定的模块性约束相冲突
However, dynamic binding violates that particular modularity constraint in a clear way.
我们考虑一下，这样会发生什么
Consider, for example, what happens over here.
假如我把next命名为别的
Suppose it was the case that I decided to change the word next.
假设两个人，一个人写sum过程，另一个人使用sum过程
Supposing somebody is writing sum, and somebody else is going to use sum.
sum的编写者有权利来选择sum内部的命名
The writer of sum has a choice of what names he may use.
假设我就是那个编写者
Let's say, I'm that writer.
刚巧，这里我不想用next来表示
Well, by gosh, just happens I didn't want to call this next.
只写一个n
I called it n.
所以下面的代码就把next都换成n
So all places where you see next, I called it n.
哎呀
Whoops.
我只是改变了过程内部的命名而已，但是整个程序就宕掉了
I changed nothing about the specifications of this program, but this program stops working.
不仅如此，这边也出现了问题
Not only that, unfortunately, this one does too.
为什么会这样？
Why do these programs stop working?
答案非常明显
Well, it's sort of clear.
为了找出nth-powers中n的值，如果根据环境模型，这个n总是这个n
Instead of chasing out the value of the n that occurs in nth power over here or over here, through the environment of definition, where this one is always linked to this one, if it was through the environment of definition, because here is the definition.
lambda表达式总在n被定义的环境下运行
This lambda expression was executed in the environment where that n was defined.
然而如果是动态绑定，我必须追踪过程的调用链，就会有糟糕的事情发生
If instead of doing that, I have to chase through the call chain, then look what horrible thing happens.
这个lambda部分其实是在sum内作为term来调用
Well, this was called from inside sum as term, term a.
这时再来查找n的定义
I'm looking for a value of n.
这样我们找到的n就不是sum-powers的n了，而变成了sum这里的n
Instead of getting this one, I get that one.
因此，在过程的内部的小小修改就导致了整个程序停止工作
So by changing the insides of this program, this program stops working.
这里的n就不再是一个量词了
So I no longer have a quantifier, as I described before.
在这个lambda里n应该是一个量词才对
The lambda symbol is supposed to be a quantifier.
一个事物所绑定的名字应该是不重要的，如果我在这里针对一个名字统一换成别的，表达式的含义也应该保持不变
A thing which has the property that the names that are bound by it are unimportant, that I can uniformly substitute any names for these throughout this thing, so long as they don't occur in here, the new names, and the meaning of this expression should remain unchanged.
但是刚才我只是对next换成了n而已，就导致nth-powers改变了意思
I've just changed the meaning of the expression by changing the one of the names.
所以这里用lambda也就不妥当了
So lambda is no longer a well defined idea.
这个问题非常严重
It's a very serious problem.
因为这个原因，我和同事们放弃了动态绑定，相对的我更喜欢模块化原则
So for that reason, I and my buddies have given up this particular kind of abstraction, which I would like to have, in favor of a modularity principle.
这也是一种针对求值器的探索
But this is the kind of experiment you can do if you want to play with these interpreters.
你可以尝试多种方法
You can try them out this way, that way, and the other way.
从中你会了解到 是什么使一个语言更加优雅
You see what makes a nicer language.
所以元循环真的很重要
So that's a very important thing to be able to do.
现在我们来想想在动态绑定的前提下 怎么样使得这里的程序可以正常运行
Now, I would like to give you a feeling for I think the right thing to do is here.
如何正确的利用动态绑定带来的好处呢？
How are you going to I get this kind of power in a lexical system?
答案是，我只想要一个针对n求指数的过程
And the answer is, of course, what I really want is a something that makes up for me an exponentiator for a particular n.
给定一个n，它就返回一个求n次方的过程
Given an n, it will make me an exponentiator.
这非常简单
Oh, but that's easy too.
换言之，我可以这样来写
In other words, I can write my program this way.
我定义一个过程PGEN，达到刚才所说的效果
I'm going to define a thing called PGEN, which is a procedure of n which produces for me an exponentiator.
(lambda (n) (lambda (x) (expt x n)))
--x to the n.
这样来写的话会更好一些，封装就不会被改名的情况而破坏了
Given that I have that, then I can capture the abstraction I wanted even better, because now it's encapsulated in a way where I can't be destroyed by a change of names.
(define sum-powers (lambda (a b n) (sum (pgen n) a 1+ b)))
I can define some powers to be a procedure again of a, b, and n which is the sum of the term function generated by using this generator, PGEN, n, with a, incrementer, and b.
再定义product-powers，(define product-powers (lambda (a b n) (product (pgen n) a 1+ b)))
And I can define the product of powers to be a procedure of a, b, and n which is the product PGEN, n, with a, increment, and b.
当然，这里的这个例子针对的抽象很简单
Now, of course, this is a very simple example where this object that I'm trying to abstract over is small.
但是这样来写的话就导致要写更多的代码
But it could be a 100 lines of code.
这样写的目的在于使其清晰一些
And so, the purpose of this is, of course, to make it simple.
确保这里的n引用的是正确的n
I'd give a name to it, it's just that here it's a parameterized name.
pgen这里的n明显的就是product-powers这里的n
It's a name that depends upon, explicitly, the lexically apparent value of n.
你也可以认为这个过程调用是一个很长的名字
So you can think of this as a long name.
这里我用一个n为参数可以生成新过程的过程来避免了之前的问题
And here, I've solved my problem by naming the term generation procedures within an n in them.
有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
你说，David
Oh, yes, David.
刚才那个问题只有这一种解决办法吗？
AUDIENCE: Is the only solution to the problem you raise to create another procedure?
换句话说，是不是只有那些过程可作为对象的语言才可以用这样的方法来解决？
In other words, can this only work in languages that are capable of defining objects as procedures?
我想想
PROFESSOR: Oh, I see.
我的解决方法是构造抽象，我没有把过程用lambda定义在sum里，而是定义在外面，然后这个过程生成一个新过程
My solution to making this abstraction, when I didn't want include the procedure inside the body, depends upon my ability to return a procedure or export one.
没错
And that's right.
如果过程作为对象，我就不能这样来解决符号冲突的问题了
If I don't have that, then I just don't have this ability to make an abstraction in a way where I don't have possibilities of symbol conflicts that were unanticipated.
你说的对
That's right.
我可以把过程作为函数返回值，也只能在过程是一类公民的语言中可以做到，这一点对于模块化编程非常重要
I consider being able to return the procedural value and, therefore, to sort of have first class procedures, in general, as being essential to doing very good modular programming.
有很多种方式来解决这个问题
Now, indeed there are many other ways to skin this cat.
你需要的做的就是考虑所有你认为糟糕的情况，然后做一个feature来解决它
What you can do is take for each of the bad things that you have to worry about, you can make a special feature that covers that thing.
你可以做一个包系统
You can make a package system.
或者像Ada中的模块系统
You can make a module system as in Ada, et cetera.
这些都可以，可能区别只是解决的程度不一
And all of those work, or they cover little regions of it.
过程作为返回值这一点可以解决所有问题，这种最简单的机制，却可以给予你最好的模块性
The thing is that returning procedures as values cover all of those problems. And so it's the simplest mechanism that gives you the best modularity, gives you all of the known modularity mechanisms.
好的，该休息一会儿了
Well, I suppose it's time for the next break, thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
昨天你们学习流的时候，哈罗德向你们提到过求值顺序与过程参数延时求值的问题
PROFESSOR: Well, yesterday when you learned about streams, Hal worried to you about the order of evaluation and delayed arguments to procedures.
我们昨天讲了流，其中调用者和被调用者都必须了解参数是被delay的，然后被调用者对参数force而得到结果
The way we played with streams yesterday, it was the responsibility of the caller and the callee to both agree that an argument was delayed, and the callee must force the argument if it needs the answer.
这样的话，过程的开发者和过程的使用者就需要太多的交流与协商
So there had to be a lot of hand shaking between the designer of a procedure and user of it over delayedness.
这看起来很糟糕，但是对于流来说没什么不妥。但是，广泛着来看，我们想要的是一个广泛层面的设计决策，而且可以显式的清晰的表述出来
That turns out, of course, to be a fairly bad thing, it works all right with streams. But as a general thing, what you want is an idea to have a locus, a decision, a design decision in general, to have a place where it's made, explicitly, and notated in a clear way.
所以，如果过程编写者和过程使用者需要花费不少的精力去协商比如参数是否求值、求值顺序的问题，那是十分不妥当的
And so it's not a very good idea to have to have an agreement, between the person who writes a procedure and the person who calls it, about such details as, maybe, the arguments of evaluation, the order of evaluation.
但是也不是太糟糕
Although, that's not so bad.
我的意思是，可能参数输入的是一个数字
I mean, we have other such agreements like, the input's a number.
但是，如果其中一个人可以全权负责这部分的事情是再好不过了
But it would be nice if only one of these guys could take responsibility, completely.
这个想法已经不算新潮了
Now this is not a new idea.
ALGOL就提供了完全不同的两种方式来执行过程
ALGOL 60 had two different ways of calling a procedure.
参数作为名称传递或者值传递
The arguments could be passed by name or by value.
按名字传递的意思即这个参数会延时求值
And what that meant was that a name argument was delayed.
当你按名字传递一个参数，只有你去取它的值的时候，它的值才会被计算出来
That when you passed an argument by name, that its value would only be obtained if you accessed that argument.
我们接下来，还要对语言进行一些小的修改
So what I'd like to do now is show you, first of all, a little bit about, again, we're going to make a modification to a language.
这里，我们再添加一个新的feature
In this case, we're going to add a feature.
可以称作为“名称参数”，或者你就理解为 延时参数 就行
We're going to add the feature of, by name parameters, if you will, or delayed parameters.
因为事实上，我们的Lisp中默认传递的是指针的值
Because, in fact, the default in our Lisp system is by the value of a pointer.
指针被复制了，但是它所指向的数据结构却没有变化 [在没有赋值与副作用的情况下，这不会造成什么影响]
A pointer is copied, but the data structure it points at is not.
我也会讲到，如何来使用名称参数
But I'd like to, in fact, show you is how you add name arguments as well.
为什么我们需要这样的feature呢？
Now again, why would we need such a thing?
语言中的保留字在eval中都属于特殊形式，假如我们开发出具有保留字那样的功能
Well supposing we wanted to invent certain kinds of what otherwise would be special forms, reserve words?
但是并不是添加新的保留字
But I'd rather not take up reserve words.
我想用一个过程来达到if的效果
I want procedures that can do things like if.
if很特殊，cond也是
If is special, or cond, or whatever it is.
它们很一样
It's the same thing.
if特殊在它会根据谓词的真假来判断是执行真语句还是假语句
It's special in that it determines whether or not to evaluate the consequent or the alternative based on the value of the predicate part of an expression.
谓词的值决定了做不做后续的事
So taking the value of one thing determines whether or not to do something else.
然而像 + 之类的过程，它们的参数可以在过程应用之前求值
Whereas all the procedures like plus, the ones that we can define right now, evaluate all of their arguments before application.
假如我现在用保留字if来定义一个与if相反含义的过程
So, for example, supposing I wish to be able to define something like the reverse of if in terms of if.
叫它unless
Call it unless.
一个谓词，一个真语句，一个假语句
We've a predicate, a consequent, and an alternative.
接下来的是，哦，我用的是cond来定义，不是if，前面说错了
Now what I would like to sort of be able to do is say-- oh, I'll do it in terms of cond.
(cond ((not p) c) (else a))
Cond, if not the predicate, then take the consequent, otherwise, take the alternative.
在这种情况下，假设我继续做下面的
Now, what I'd like this to mean, is supposing I do something like this.
(unless (= 1 0) 2 (/ 1 0))
I'd like this unless say if equals one, 0, then the answer is two, otherwise, the quotient of one and 0.
接下来要做的是进行代换，下面的1 2 3参数分别对应上面的p c a
What I'd like that to mean is the result of substituting equal one, 0, and two, and the quotient of one, 0 for p, c, and a.
代换过后就像是，(cond ((not (= 1 0)) 2) (else (/ 1 0)))
I'd like that to mean, and this is funny, I'd like it to transform into or mean cond not equal one, 0, then the result is two, otherwise I want it to be the quotient one and 0.
如果你直接把cond这一部分输入Lisp，会得到结果2
Now, you know that if I were to type this into Lisp, I'd get a two.
没问题
There's no problem with that.
然而，如果我把unless这一部分输入Lisp，参数会在过程执行之前先求值，这样(/ 1 0)这里就会报错
However, if I were to type this into Lisp, because all the arguments are evaluated before I start, then I'm going to get an error out of this.
如果代换为cond，我可以得到正确的结果
So that if the substitutions work at all, of course, I would get the right answer.
但是这里这种情况，代换并不能进行
But here's a case where the substitutions don't work.
我得到了错误的结果
I don't get the wrong answer.
没结果
I get no answer.
还是一个错误
I get an error.
现在，我要想办法使这样的定义可以成功运行
Now, however, I'd like to be able to make my definition so that this kind of thing works.
这里我要对 c 和 a 动点手脚
What I want to do is say something special about c and a.
我想使它们自动延时求值
I want them to be delayed automatically.
不想使它们在执行过程之前就求值
I don't want them to be evaluated at the time I call.
所以按照惯例，我先构造一种语法描述，之后我们再来具体的实现它
So I'm going to make a declaration, and then I'm going to see how to implement such a declaration.
你们应该深信，我正在添加一个有趣的kluge[不知怎么译的准确]
But again, I want you to say to yourself, oh, this is an interesting kluge he's adding in here.
太多的kluge会使得系统混乱复杂
The piles of kluges make a big complicated mess.
还会搞砸以后要添加的功能
And is this going to foul up something else that might occur.
新的语法描述，先来看，是否有语法上混淆的问题
First of all, is it syntactically unambiguous?
当然，这里我要写的是一个清晰的无二义的新语法
Well, it will be syntactically unambiguous with what we've seen so far.
但是接下来要做的却会导致另外的问题
But what I'm going to do may, in fact, cause trouble.
可能以后我们会为了优化系统或者编译器而引入类型声明的机制，我一会儿要定义的新语法可能会与之冲突
It may be that the thing I had will conflict with type declarations I might want to add in the future for giving some system, some compiler or something, the ability to optimize given the types are known.
或者会与那些声明参数类型这样的机制相冲突
Or it might conflict with other types of declarations I might want to make about the formal parameters.
所以我这里要添加的机制并不是一个完整的机制
So I'm not making a general mechanism here where I can add declarations.
只是能解决目前的问题而已
And I would like to be able to do that.
具体怎么样完整就不在这里说了
But I don't want to talk about that right now.
接下来
So here I'm going to do, I'm going to build a kluge.
我再来定义unless，一个谓词，真真假语句都按名称来传递，即(name c) (name a)
So we're going to define unless of a predicate-- and I'm going to call these by name-- the consequent, and name the alternative.
哦没估计好，卡在黑板边了
Huh, huh-- I got caught in the corner.
(cond ((not p) c) (else a))
If not p then the result is c, else-- that's what I'd like.
我可以显式的来声明，哪些参数按名称传递延时求值
Where I can explicitly declare certain of the parameters to be delayed, to be computed later.
这样的话，要对求值器做出的修改可就比之前的feature要复杂多了
Now, this is actually a very complicated modification to an interpreter rather than a simple one.
之前的动态绑定，或者不定参数，相比比较简单
The ones you saw before, dynamic binding or adding indefinite argument procedures, is relatively simple.
但是这里，是一个基本原则的改变
But this one changes a basic strategy.
我们之前的解释器，解释组合式时，先求值操作符，再求值操作数，最后再用操作符应用于操作数得到结果
The problem here is that our interpreter, as written, evaluates a combination by evaluating the procedure, the operator producing the procedure, and evaluating the operands producing the arguments, and then doing apply of the procedure to the arguments.
然而这里，在我检测过整个过程的声明之前，我并不想立即求值操作数
However, here, I don't want to evaluate the operands to produce the arguments until after I examined the procedure to see what the procedure's declarations look like.
我们来看这个
So let's look at that.
对求值器的修改
Here we have a changed evaluator.
这是从最开始的那个求值器修改得来的，不是动态绑定的那个  这里的修改和之前的有些相似
I'm starting with the simple lexical evaluator, not dynamic, but we're going to have to do something sort of similar in some ways.
如果我延时一个过程 -- 哦说错了 -- 延时一个过程的参数，就必须把当前的环境和参数关联在一起
Because of the fact that, if I delay a procedure-- I'm sorry-- delay an argument to a procedure, I'm going to have to attach and environment to it.
还记得哈罗德教授是怎么实现delay的吧
Remember how Hal implemented delay.
哈罗德教授把delay实现为一个没有参数的过程，其中包含了要延时的操作
Hal implemented delay as being a procedure of no arguments which does some expression.
就像这样
That's what delay of the expression is.
(delay e)
--of that expression.
返回下面的(lambda () e)
This turned into something like this.
然而，我要执行这个lambda，就必须要在一定的环境下
Now, however, if I evaluate a lambda expression, I have to capture the environment.
原因是因为其中有一些自由变量只有在正确的上下文中才能正确解读
The reason why is because there are variables in there who's meaning I wish to derive from the context where this was written.
这也是 用lambda来实现delay的原因
So that's why a lambda does the job.
非常合适
It's the right thing.
相对应的，对延时对象force就是执行这个无参数的过程
And such that the forcing of a delayed expression was same thing as calling that with no arguments.
和上面恰恰相对
It's just the opposite of this.
为过程调用生成了新的环境就是在过程定义的时候所附加的新frame
Producing an environment of the call which is, in fact, the environment where this was defined with an extra frame in it that's empty.
这里就不细细讨论了
I don't care about that.
我们再来看这张幻灯片，仔细看一会儿，会发现大部分都是相同的，只有最下面处理组合式的地方不同
Well, if we go back to this slide, since it's the case, if we look at this for a second, everything is the same as it was before except the case of applications or combinations.
这种情况有两个部分
And combinations are going to do two things.
一是我得先求值操作符
One, is I have to evaluate the procedure-- forget the procedure-- by evaluating the operator.
也就是这一部分
That's what you see right here.
这里我要保证它已经被求出值的，也即用undelay来确保操作符不再是延时对象
I have to make sure that that's current, that is not a delayed object, and evaluate that to the point where it's forced now.
然后应用于操作数
And then I have to somehow apply that to the operands.
这里还要保存下当前的环境，作为第三个参数传递过去
But I have to keep the environment, pass that environmental along.
如果有一些参数是延时了的
So some of those operands I may have to delay.
就需要用此时的环境来求值
I may have to attach that environment to those operands.
看起来已经十分复杂了
This is a rather complicated thing happening here.
再来看看apply
Looking at that in apply.
这一部分还是判断基本过程，和之前一样
Apply, well it has a primitive procedure thing just like before.
组合过程的部分就比较有意思了
But the compound one is a little more interesting.
我要在过程定义时绑定的环境下求值过程，但是参数要在和延时参数关联起来的环境下求值
I have to evaluate the body, just as before, in an environment which is the result of binding some formal parameters to arguments in the environment.
两个环境
That's true.
这个环境是定义过程时关联的环境
The environment is the one that comes from the procedure now.
静态绑定
It's a lexical language, statically bound.
我还需要的是去掉name声明，获得变量的实际名字
However, one thing I have to do is strip off the declarations to get the names of the variables.
也就是vnames过程所要做的
That's what this guy does, vnames.
然后要做的就是，这些操作数，哪些要马上求值，哪些要先用延时封装起来
And the other thing I have to do is process these declarations, deciding which of these operands-- that's the operands now, as opposed to the arguments-- which of these operands to evaluate, and which of them are to be encapsulated in delays of some sort.
另外，如果遇到的基本过程，操作数还是要马上求值
The other thing you see here is that we got a primitive, a primitive like plus, had better get at the real operands.
也就是这里
So here is a place where we're going to have to force them.
evlist中其中做了很多force的工作
And we're going to look at what evlist is going to have to do a bunch of forces.
所以这里有两个evlist
So we have two different kinds of evlist now.
evlist和gevlist gevlist对要延时的参数加以封装，对其它的则马上求值
We have evlist and gevlist. Gevlist is going to wrap delays around some things and force others, evaluate others.
evlist的话就是单纯的去求值
And this guy's going to do some forcing of things.
来看evlist，这里我们只需做我们自己的事就行，大家已经很熟悉了
Just looking at this a little bit, this is a game you must play for yourself, you know.
这里不会有求值器传递过来的多种情况
It's not something that you're going to see all possible variations on an evaluator talking to me.
我们只需要一味求值就可以了
What you have to do is do this for yourself.
在你感觉过这种方式之后，你将会看到另一种方式，这里你需要处理不同的设计决策，了解它们的具体意思，清楚它们如何相互关联
And after you feel this, you play this a bit, you get to see all the possible design decisions and what they might mean, and how they interact with each other.
任何语言都是这样
So what languages might have in them.
普遍通用的规则与少量特殊的规则，协同构建一门合理的语言
And what are some of the consistent sets that make a legitimate language.
然后如果有太多的kluge，就会对语言造成破坏
Whereas what things are complicated kluges that are just piles of junk.
回到evlist上来，针对所有的操作数force求值
So evlist of course, over here, just as I said, is a list of operands which are going to be undelayed after evaluation.
无论操作数是否是延时对象
So these are going to be forced, whatever that's going to mean.
下一个，gevlist
And gevlist, which is the next thing-- Thank you.
这里，就会发现有很多种情况
What we see here, well there's a couple of possibilities.
如果不是用name延时的参数，就像unless中谓词部分，对应这一部分代码
Either it's a normal, ordinary thing, a symbol sitting there like the predicate in the unless, and that's what we have here.
这一部分就使用应用序求值
In which case, this is intended to be evaluated in applicative order.
就像以前一样
And it's, essentially, just what we had before.
然后递归求值，就是对CAR求值之后，再用gevlist对剩下的求值
It's mapping eval down the list. In other words, I evaluate the first expression and continue gevlisting the CDR of the expression in the environment.
然而，有可能我们遇到一个延时参数
However, it's possible that this is a name parameter.
如果是一个延时参数，就delay这个参数，还要记得封装当前的环境
If it's a name parameter, I want to put a delay in which combines that expression, which I'm calling by name, with the environment that's available at this time and passing that as the parameter.
然后继续递归
And this is part of the mapping process that you see here.
另一个有意思的地方是evcond
The only other interesting place in this interpreter is cond.
人们可能认为这一部分没什么特别的，就草草写完
People tend to write this thing, and then they leave this one out.
这里有一个地方是需要force的，值得注意
There's a place where you have to force.
条件式必须先知道谓词的真假
Conditionals have to know whether or not the answer is true or false.
就像一个基本过程一样
It's like a primitive.
当你定义条件式的时候，你必须需要force
When you do a conditional, you have to force.
剩下的细节就没什么特别的了
Now, I'm not going to look at any more of this in any detail.
就先不深究了
It isn't very exciting.
剩下的就是delay的实现了
And what's left is how you make delays.
delay就是一个数据结构，其中包括了类型'trunk，表达式和环境
Well, delays are data structures which contain an expression, an environment, and a type on them.
'thunk标明这是一个trunk
And it says they're a thunk.
是从ALGOL借用过来的，原义大概是把什么压在栈中
That comes from ALGOL language, and it's claimed to be the sound of something being pushed on a stack.
记不清了
I don't know.
我对ALGOL了解的不深入
I was not an ALGOLician or an ALGOLite or whatever, so I don't know.
但是我们就在这里借用它了
But that's what was claimed.
undelay不断递归的force求值，直到遇到不是'trunk的对象
And undelay is something which will recursively undelay thunks until the thunk becomes something which isn't a thunk.
这就是具体的实现
This is the way you implement a call by name like thing in ALGOL.
全部都在这里了
And that's about all there is.
有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
Gerry？
AUDIENCE: Gerry?
你说，Vesko
PROFESSOR: Yes, Vesko?
我注意到，在调用基本过程的时候，你避免用名字传递参数，这样做有什么原因吗？
AUDIENCE: I noticed you avoided calling by name in the primitive procedures, I was wondering what cause you have on that?
需要这样吗？
You never need that?
Vesko想问的是 基本过程的参数如果按名字传递是否合理？
PROFESSOR: Vesko is asking if it's ever reasonable to call a primitive procedure by name?
答案是 是的
The answer is, yes.
有一种情况下是可以的，哦两种
There's one particular case where it's reasonable, actually two.
比如用cons来构建一个数组的数据结构
Construction of a data structure like cons where making an array if you have arrays with any number of elements.
没必要求值参数
It's unnecessary to evaluate those arguments.
你只需要一个约定，一个需要计算参数的时候就可以得到结果的约定
All you need is promises to evaluate those arguments if you look at them.
如果我用cons把两个东西连接起来，连接两个约定和连接两个实际的东西一样简单
If I cons together two things, then I could cons together the promises just as easily as I can cons together the things.
甚至在用CAR CDR取出的时候也不用计算
And it's not even when I CAR CDR them that I have to look at them.
直接把约定传递给其它人
That just gets out the promises and passes them to somebody.
这也是阿隆佐 丘奇用lambda演算定义的cons能够说得通的原因
That's why the lambda calculus definition, the Alonzo Church definition of CAR, CDR, and cons makes sense.
因为在cons car cdr中并没有什么计算，它们不过是存东西取东西而已
It's because no work is done in CAR, CDR, and cons, it's just shuffling data, it's just routing, if you will.
然而像 + 这样的过程必须要了解参数是什么
However, the things that do have to look at data are things like plus.
因为 + 需要和实际组成数字的比特打交道，如果遇到一个lambda就搞笑了
Because they have a look at the bits that the numbers are made out of, unless they're lambda calculus numbers which are funny.
它要从数字的比特层面来实际计算
They have to look at the bits to be able to crunch them together to do the add.
可能在一种最懒惰的解释器实现中，数据构造器，数据选择器，包括像有副作用的一些对象都是不需要force求值的
So, in fact, data constructors, data selectors, and, in fact, things that side-effect data objects don't need to do any forcing in the laziest possible interpreters.
话说回来判断数据结构的谓词还是需要force的
On the other hand predicates on data structures have to.
这是一个序对吗？
Is this a pair?
或者是一个符号？
Or is it a symbol?
最好搞清楚是什么
Well, you better find out.
这点还是挺重要的
You got to look at it then.
还有问题吗？
Any other questions?
没了，下面是休息时间
Oh, well, I suppose it's time for a break.
下课
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]